Let’s move now to the last part of this
lecture, focusing on bugs and how they can
be exploited by adversaries.
In this case, we will focus on a specific
type of attack, the buffer overflow attack.
Before focusing on buffer overflow attacks,
let me focus on some general considerations.
It should be clear that cracking a password
is only one way to gain control from the attacker's
perspective. There can be alternative ways,
which even require fewer efforts in some cases.
One of them is to manage to trick the user
into doing something that will harm him/her,
and this could be done by infecting the browser,
have users download malicious content, and
so on...
The other is to exploit bugs, which are definitely
there in Operating Systems.
Let’s focus now on buffer overflow attacks.
First, we need to know that the C programming
language does not perform array bounds checks.
If we want to be sure we do not write in an
array (a buffer of characters, for instance)
something that is larger than the array itself,
we need to do that explicitly.
Second, we need to remember that the stack
of a process grows downwards, from the last
address to smaller ones.
Let’s see now what is happening.
When we jump from the main function to a different
function, we need to keep track of where we
were, so that we can get back there once the
function has completed its execution. We do
this by writing a return address.
After such a return address, we will have
the various variables used by the function
(A in the example).
Among these, we can have a buffer B.
If a malicious user is aware of this and also
has the chance of giving back to the procedure
A what should be written inside B, then it
can give a longer input. This input can overwrite
the return address.
In this case, the attacker can put a predefined
value there, even pointing to an address within
the input he/she just provided.
The code available there would then be executed
next.
It turns out some system calls from the OS
suffer from this bug. If the return address
is changed to point to an injected code that
starts a terminal, a malicious user can have
access with full privileges to the computer
(because the system call was being run by
the operating system itself)
A way to detect possible attacks (that is
not 100% secure) is to use stack canaries.
In this case, just below the return address,
we can add a random value and compile programs
with special code that will stop the execution
if such value is changed.
The idea is that when overflowing the buffer,
the attacker will also change such random
value, and the program will be able to detect
this.
As I mention in the slide, you can check in
the book how stack canaries can be avoided.
Alternative ways to go include the no-execute
bit, which in this case is based on the hardware
itself and used to specify portions of memory
that cannot contain executable parts.
In this case, it is possible to prevent code
injection attacks (because no code will be
executed).